{"tossups": [{"question": "1. In this non-French civilization\u2019s homes, elevated platforms known to scholars as lits clos are thought to have been household altars for ritual prayer or beds. Maturing children in this civilization shaved their heads entirely except for three strands braided into an S-shape, called the \u201csidelock of youth.\u201d Households in this civilization kept amulets of dwarves with the mane, ears, and tail of a large feline for protection. This civilization set its calendar according to the heliacal rising of Sirius. Nearly everyone in this civilization wore (*) powdered galena and malachite as eyeliner. Both nobility and commoners in this civilization played a game on a 10-by-3 board based on throwing sticks or bones as \u201cdice.\u201d People in this civilization used Bes images for household protection and played senet to pass time. For 10 points, name this ancient civilization that worshipped its pharaohs.", "answer": "(Ancient) Egyptian civilization [or Kemet] &lt;AA, Ancient History&gt;", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "2. This author commanded \u201cGather the flowers, but spare the buds\u201d in order to avoid the ire of Flora, who would \u201cNip in the blossom all our hopes and thee.\u201d The speaker of a poem titled for this author describes how the \u201ccurving east\u201d experiences the \u201cearthly chill of dusk and slow\u201d and an \u201cever climbing shadow grow.\u201d This author of \u201cThe Picture of Little T. C. in a Prospect of Flowers\u201d titles a poem whose speaker feels \u201cthe always coming on / the (*) rising of the night\u201d while \u201cface down beneath the sun.\u201d This author noted \u201cThus, though we cannot make our sun / stand still, yet we will make him run\u201d in a poem that inspired an Archibald MacLeish poem titled after him. For 10 points, name this author who wrote of \u201cdeserts of vast eternity\u201d and \u201cTime\u2019s winged chariot\u201d in \u201cTo His Coy Mistress.\u201d", "answer": "Andrew Marvell [accept \u201cYou, Andrew Marvell\u201d] &lt;WA, Poetry&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "3. Systems of accounting and cosmology developed by speakers of these languages are the main subject of Gary Burton\u2019s studies, which focus on muyu circles. It\u2019s not Japanese, but children of northern nobility were forced to move south, live in the capital, and learn these languages in a process of assimilation called mitima. Myths among speakers of these languages tell of Inkarri, who founded a lost refuge city in the east called Paititi. An empire run by speakers of these languages codified the (*) ayllu kinship structure which they shared with the neighboring Aymara. Speakers of these languages denote sacred sites as wakas, runners that staffed a great road system as chasquis, and knots used to perform math as khipus. For 10 points, name these Andean languages used in the Inca empire.", "answer": "Quechuan languages [or Quechua or Runasimi] &lt;WA, Historical Sources&gt;", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "The introduction to a play titled for this concept quotes R. W. Johnson\u2019s negative review of The Pity of War in describing the attitude of a character first played by Stephen Campbell Moore. In that play titled for this concept, the phrase \u201cFuck the Renaissance\u201d is spoken during the dismissal of a character who earlier borrows a phrase from Proverbs 9, \u201cbread eaten in secret,\u201d to describe General Studies. Motorcycle rides are used as occasions to fondle boys\u2019 genitals in a play titled for this concept that is set at (*) Cutlers\u2019 Grammar school and features the teachers Mr. Irwin and Mr. Hector. Alan Bennett wrote a 2004 play titled for this concept, which also names the genre of a play in which the line \u201cI am determined to prove a villain\u201d is spoken by a hunchback king who exclaims \u201cmy kingdom for a horse!\u201d For 10 points, William Shakespeare wrote comedies, tragedies, and plays about what subject?", "answer": "history [or histories; accept The History Boys] &lt;WA, Drama&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "5. A female ruler of this empire was killed when her servants were replaced by women with wooden pikes, who beat her to death. After an effort at modernization, this empire\u2019s army consisted of levies, Fauj-i-Ain [FOWJ-ee-YNE] regulars, and Fauj-i-Khas elite troops; it was also the last major military power to rely on feudal jagirdar horsemen. Thanks to a betrayal by two Dogra generals, this empire lost the Battle of Sobraon to an invading power, though its first leader defeated an invasion led by Zaman Shah Durrani. It consisted of a group of autonomous confederated states called (*) misls and had elite troops such as the Akalis. This empire was first governed as a unified polity from Lahore by Maharaja Ranjit, who was crowned by Sahib Singh Bed. For 10 points, name this empire in the Punjab whose army was known as the Khalsa.", "answer": "Sikh empire [or Panjab empire or Sikh Khalsa Raj] &lt;EM, World History&gt;", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "6. In a novel named after one of these people, a girl dislikes the pronunciation of \u201cnasty\u201d as \u201cnesty\u201d by a policewoman whom she privately names Sergeant Anne Grey. Another one of these people, who repeatedly says \u201cumph,\u201d sees his future wife standing on a ledge and hurts his ankle in a mistaken effort to help her. When asked whether her biggest influence was political, personal, or Calvinism, the nun who wrote \u201cThe Transfiguration of the Commonplace\u201d replies that it was a person with this job who manipulated a girl into having an affair with the artist (*) Teddy Lloyd. E. R. Braithwaite wrote a novel about his experience in this profession. A woman of this profession is fired for Fascist sympathies and has a namesake \u201cset\u201d of students including Rose and Sandy. A Muriel Spark book explores the \u201cprime\u201d of a woman in, for 10 points, what profession of Mr. Chips and Miss Jean Brodie?", "answer": "teachers [or educators; do not accept or prompt on \u201cprofessors\u201d] &lt;JC, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "7. A writing by this man relates how a pillar with Syrian characters was erected for the burial of Pantheia and Abradatas. Gilbert Murray gave the name of \u201cOld Oligarch\u201d to an author usually identified as a \u201cpseudo\u201d version of this man, which criticizes Athens\u2019 constitution for promoting social vice. A history by this man covers events leading up to the Battle of Mantinea after the final seven years of the Peloponnesian War. Another of his works attributes qualities of an (*) ideal ruler to the conqueror of Astyages and the Medes, and is one of the most important Greek examples of the \u201cmirror for princes\u201d genre. This author of the Hellenica and Cyropaedia wrote an account in which he joined Cyrus the Younger\u2019s war against his brother as part of the Ten Thousand, a group of mercenaries. For 10 points, name this author of the Anabasis.", "answer": "Xenophon [accept Pseudo-Xenophon] &lt;WA, Historiography&gt;", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "8. In the first conversation in T. S. Eliot\u2019s \u201cPortrait of a Lady,\u201d it is remarked that this man\u2019s soul \u201cshould be resurrected only among friends.\u201d An autobiographical novel depicts this man and his family staying in the charterhouse of Valdemossa, hoping his tuberculosis would improve. His letters recount a failed engagement to a woman named Maria, after which he traveled to London with Camille Pleyel. A Cyprian Norwid poem depicts an incident in which an object owned by this man was thrown out of a window in (*) January 1863. A vacation with this man is recounted in the novel Winter in Majorca. Amusingly, a work by this non-Wagner musician is performed by Mademoiselle Reisz in a novel by an American author who surname is spelled the same way, and who also wrote \u201cDesiree\u2019s Baby.\u201d For 10 points, name this musically talented lover of George Sand, a native of Poland.", "answer": "Frederic Chopin &lt;WA, HistInLit&gt;", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "9. After scoring a permit related to these animals, television personality Steven Rinella spent years researching a book about them as an \u201cicon.\u201d The immigrant \u201cScotty\u201d Philip is best known for creating a preserve for these animals. A novel titled for these animals by Patrick Gainville follows George Catlin\u2019s efforts to depict them. As part of an effort to beautify U.S. (*) coinage, James Earl Philips designed a nickel depicting them that was minted until 1938. At the request of his wife, Charles Goodnight kept a number of these animals captive starting in 1866. Don and Teach attempt to steal the title valuable coin named for these animals in a play by David Mamet. For 10 points, name these large quadrupeds which once roamed throughout the Great Plains.", "answer": "American buffalo [or bison; do not accept or prompt on \u201cwater buffalo\u201d] &lt;WA, US History&gt;", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "10. Rabbi Daniel Zion praised this country\u2019s monarch for refusing to capitulate to demands of such foreign officials as Theodor Dannecker. It\u2019s not Austria, but a corporatist movement in this country overthrew a wartime regime in the September 9 coup to establish its Fatherland Front. Pro-fascist irredentists who led this country, and who were opposed by a [emphasize] neighboring country\u2019s IMRO group, sought to expand it to a \u201cGreater\u201d version. This country\u2019s (*) Rila Monastery served as the burial site of its penultimate king, who was probably poisoned at the height of World War II and named Boris III. The Communist regime that took over this country in World War II was led by Georgi Dimitrov and later by noted Turk-hater Todor Zhivkov, who ran it for four decades. For 10 points, name this Balkan country governed from Sofia.", "answer": "(Kingdom of) Bulgaria [or Republic of Bulgaria] &lt;WA, Continental History&gt;", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "11. This novel\u2019s opening paragraph is replaced with a word noting the recent slaughter of 18 people in a 2009 adaptation. A man in this novel forces an issue by saying \u201cYou are too generous to trifle with me\u2026 one word from you will silence me on this subject forever\u201d while alluding to sentiments from \u201clast April,\u201d and earlier meditates on the pleasure bestowed by the \u201cfine eyes\u201d of a woman he adores. In a key scene in this novel, a man says (*) \u201cIn vain I have struggled.\u00a0It will not do\u201d during a proposal. A 2016 film adapts Seth Grahame-Smith\u2019s version of this novel, which introduces undead to its plot. A bachelor\u2019s move to Netherfield Park begins the plot of this novel, which notes \u201cIt is a truth universally acknowledged\u201d that certain men \u201cmust be in want of a wife.\u201d For 10 points, Mr. Bingley marries Jane and Fitzwilliam marries Elizabeth in what Jane Austen novel?", "answer": "Pride and Prejudice [accept Pride and Prejudice and Zombies] &lt;WA, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "12. In an essay, this author noted that the frequent use of the phrase \u201cmore to come\u201d is an example of how one can easily become accustomed to having \u201cmore than you might want.\u201d In another essay, this author wrote about how he could not communicate with a hotel clerk who only spoke a dialect that was native to Kefiristan during the time of Alexander the Great. In that essay, he recalls repeatedly removing bottles of alcohol from a minibar to store a (*) cooked fish he bought at the airport. An essay by this author begins by attributing the success of holography to a country\u2019s obsession with realism and uses the term \"fortress of solitude\" to describe structures like the LBJ Library and Disneyland. In a novel, this author of Travels in Hyperreality wrote of Belbo, Diotallevi and Casaubon, who invent a conspiracy theory known as \"The Plan.\" For 10 points name this Italian semiotician who wrote Foucault's Pendulum.", "answer": "Umberto Eco &lt;SB, Essays/Crit&gt;", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "13. In the Orkney Islands, ritual offerings made of this material were known as Skaill knives. Methods of modifying this material include the \u201cbipolar reduction\u201d technique. The Barnhouse Settlement is near Loch Stenness, a UNESCO World Heritage site containing several objects made of this material known as menhirs. This material can be finely shaped using the soft hammer percussion technique as part of (*) knapping. Furniture made of this material is found in the well-preserved Skara Brae village in Scotland. Charles II was given a tour of one site containing this material, Avebury, by John Aubrey, the namesake of 56 holes surrounding the most famous monument comprised of this material in Britain. For 10 points, name this material first adapted for tools in the Paleolithic period that names a \u201chenge\u201d in England.", "answer": "stone [or rock; accept Stonehenge; anti-prompt on specific varieties of stone or rock like flint or chert; do not accept or prompt on \u201cmarble\u201d] &lt;AA, Archaeology&gt;", "category": "History"}, {"question": "14. In a poem, one of these characters is asked if \u201cinnumerable speechless dead\u201d would cast their \u201ceternally / valid coins of happiness\u201d before a pair of true lovers on a \u201csilent carpet,\u201d if there were a \u201cplace we know nothing of.\u201d Another poem posits that if one of these characters \u201ctook even one step down towards us / our own heart\u201d would \u201cbeat us to death.\u201d A third poem implies that neither these characters nor humans are aware, unlike the \u201cinsightful animals,\u201d that we are not \u201cat home in our interpreted world.\u201d A poem notes that \u201cI would be (*) consumed in that overwhelming existence\u201d if one of these beings \u201cpressed me against his heart.\u201d Echoing the poem that precedes it, an assertion that every one of these beings \u201cis terrifying\u201d opens a German poem. For 10 points, the first Duino elegy asks \u201cWho, if I cried out, would hear me\u201d among the \u201corders\u201d of what celestial beings?", "answer": "angels [or engelen] &lt;WA, Poetry&gt;", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "15. This was the self-appointed title of a former British paratrooper who fought under the pseudonym \u201cTony Callan\u201d in the Angolan Civil War. From 1926 to 1939, the Second Polish Republic was led by J\u00f3zef Pi\u0142sudski\u2019s subordinates with this title. In an extremely popular military mashup, the lyrics to the song \u201cHitler Has Only Got One Ball\u201d were set to the tune of a march named after this title. This title is the highest honorary title of a U.S. state, which has bestowed it on such men as Jim Beam. A regime named for men of this title forced (*) Constantine II out of his job as king while ruling from 1967 to 1974 in Greece. Upon gaining control of the Revolutionary Command Council, Muammar Gaddafi gave himself this honorific military title. Civil War regiments were commanded by, for 10 points, what military rank below general whose honorary Kentuckian bearers included Harlan Sanders?", "answer": "colonels [accept colonel-in-chief or \u201cColonel Bogey\u2019s March\u201d or Syntagmatarch\u00f3n] &lt;AA, British/Other History&gt;", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "16. In one work, this character\u2019s wife carries a crocodile\u2019s mouth as a handbag to represent the \u201cbattle between the paper shredders and the photostat machines.\u201d That work by Jane Taylor pairs this character with the post-apartheid \u201cTruth Commission.\u201d In a play, this character repeatedly exclaims \u201cby my green candle\u201d and holds a race for a chest of gold that is won by Michel Federovitch; he later throws a bunch of nobles into the Debraining Machine. This man\u2019s wife pretends to be the angel Gabriel to scare him before they knock down Bougrelas with a dead bear and escape to (*) France. This character, who was supposedly based on a hated physics teacher, begins his play by yelling \u201cMerdre!\u201d This man, who is primarily a parody of Macbeth, kills the king of Poland. For 10 points, name this titular Roi of an Alfred Jarry satire.", "answer": "Pere Ubu [accept Ubu Roi] &lt;JC, Drama&gt;", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "17. In a story by this author, the aspiring novelist of The Chelsea Set is so engrossed in talk with her fianc\u00e9e that she ignores the title figures who speak an \u201cincomprehensible tongue\u201d while eating a fish dinner at Bentley\u2019s. A character created by this author maintains a \u201cbrooding silence\u201d for an entire summer with a group of boys who laugh at his name, so that character goes by the initial \u201cT.\u201d This author of \u201cThe Invisible Japanese Gentlemen\u201d wrote a story in which \u201cOld Misery\u201d is targeted by the (*) Wormsley Common Gang, who plan to blow up his house in the aftermath of the Blitz. Spicer, Dallow, and Cubit are members of another gang created by this author whose leader is hunted by Ida Arnold. This author of \u201cThe Destructors\u201d used the name of a candy to title his novel about Pinkie Brown. For 10 points, name this author of Brighton Rock and The Power and the Glory.", "answer": "Graham Greene &lt;WA, Short Fiction&gt;", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "18. In September 2017, India began a project that would use the E5 series of these things in Mumbai and Ahmedabad. In a classic example of pork-barrel politics, Tanaka Kakuei directed millions in government money to bring these things to Joetsu. The first use of these things was scheduled to coincide with the opening of the 1964 Summer Olympics. In 1987, the state-owned company that operates these things was privatized and became the (*) JR Group. After 2005, these things were able to operate in the Seikan Tunnel thanks to a dual-gauge extension. These things, whose name literally means \u201cnew trunk line,\u201d would run on the proposed Ch\u016b\u014d line, which would operate maglev service from Tokyo to Nagoya. For 10 points, name this extremely fast form of land transportation used in Japan.", "answer": "bullet trains [or Shinkansen or Superexpress; accept New Trunk Line before it is read; prompt on trains or high-speed trains; do not accept or prompt on \u201cmetro\u201d or \u201csubway\u201d] &lt;WA, World History&gt;", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "19. Convinced that nobility were descended from Trojans, this author portrayed the latter as malevolent in such works as Letter of Othea to Hector. A book by this author opens with a frame tale in which the autobiographical protagonist goes to dinner after seeing a copy of Matheolus\u2019s Lamentations. The spirits that inspired the completion of this author\u2019s first book supposedly harassed this author into writing the education manual The Book of the Three Virtues. This author criticized mischaracterizations in such works as (*) Ovid\u2019s Art of Love and Jean de Meun\u2019s Romance of the Rose in a vernacular French book in which Reason, Rectitude, and Justice tell her to fight prejudice and build the title structure from the blocks of other famous women. For 10 points, name this author of The Book of the City of Ladies.", "answer": "Christine de Pisan [or Christine de Pizan] &lt;WA, Authors/Bios&gt;", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "20. Joseph Opala noted similarities between rice dishes prepared by people of this ethnicity and inhabitants of Bence Island an ocean away. A translation of the Bilali Diary was made during Lorenzo Turner\u2019s extensive studies of this ethnic group, which involved visits to Hog Hammock. They are the subject of the film Daughters of the Dust. Robert Winslow Gordon recorded these people as the originators of the folk song \u201cKum Bah Yah.\u201d A popular (*) Nickelodeon show in the 1980s followed a family of this ethnicity. This U.S. ethnic group\u2019s language is almost identical to dialects spoken in the Bahamas and Sierra Leone. Michelle Obama and Clarence Thomas are among notable Americans to descent from, for 10 points, what group of African descent with a distinctive creole language that inhabit the Sea Islands near Georgia and South Carolina?", "answer": "Gullah people [or Geechee people; accept Sea Island people or equivalents before \u201cSea Islands\u201d; accept Gullah Gullah Island; prompt on black people or African-Americans] &lt;WA, US History&gt;", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "21. A discussion with one of these people to bring about \u201cfriendship instead of war\u201d is documented in the Seventh Letter of Plato. These people are pitiable because they are enslaved to their personal desires and are thus doomed to commit evil according to the Gorgias. The spirit of these people is compared to the spirit of \u201cthe drunken man\u201d in Book Ten of the Republic, whose ninth book remarks that these people must always be starting wars. Pythagoras likely fled Samos because of one of these people named (*) Polycrates. Plato argued that these people naturally arise in democracy, first as \u201csmiling protectors.\u201d Historians praised two lovers named Harmodius and Aristogeiton for killing one of these people named Hipparchus. For 10 points, identify these people, whom Plato and Aristotle defined as autocrats who rule without law.", "answer": "tyrants [accept tyrannos or tyrannoi; prompt on Pesistratids or rulers or politicians] &lt;WA, Phil/SS&gt;", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "22. In an autobiographical novel, this author wrote about how he used an axe to try to kill a girl who wouldn\u2019t show him her journals when he was five years old. This author wrote one novel in a room surrounded by reproductions of the Isenheim Altarpiece. A hunchbacked dwarf plays chess at the Stars of Heaven bar and frequents the Theresianum pawn shop in one of his novels. This author created a character who takes interest in a small boy after he learns about their mutual interest in Chinese (*) literature. In that novel, the housekeeper, Therese, conspires with Benedikt Pfaff to remove a man who has imaginary conversations with Confucius from his own house. The protagonist of that novel takes routine walks around neighborhood bookstores so he won\u2019t add any more books to his 25,000 amount collection, which he later burns down. For 10 points name this creator of the sinologist Peter Kiene in Auto-da-F\u00e9.", "answer": "Elias Canetti &lt;SB, LongFic&gt;", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "23. The Ten Commandments of this organization stipulated that its members must be available for it \u201ceven if [his] wife\u2019s about to give birth.\u201d A 1963 car bombing called the Ciaculli Massacre led to a series of high-profile prosecutions of this organization\u2019s members. John Dickie wrote a history of this organization, which was flushed out in the Siege of Gangi [GAHN-jee] by an \u201cIron Prefect.\u201d A crackdown on this organization prompted an urban legend about its cooperation with (*) Operation Husky. The area in which this organization operated originated the code of silence known as omert\u00e0. During Prohibition, members of this group emigrated to America and consolidated into the Five Families. For 10 points, name this syndicate that still controls many businesses and politicians around Palermo.", "answer": "(Sicilian) Mafia [or La Cosa Nostra] &lt;AA, Continental History&gt;", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "24. After moving to this city, Alfred Chester fell in love with a fisherman and dedicated his novel The Exquisite Corpse to him. In a setting inspired by this real-life city, a conversation about the import of whale detritus to be used as a sexual lubricant takes place between Marv and Leif the Unlucky. While living in this city, a writer got extremely high in order to write a death scene set in a French prison in which typhoid claims the life of Port Moresby. The author of (*) The Sheltering Sky, Paul Bowles, lived in this city for five decades. In a setting inspired by this real-life city, the narrator visits the \u201cMerchant of Sex\u201d A.\u00a0J. and is employed by Islam Incorporated. This city\u2019s International Zone inspired Interzone, the setting of Naked Lunch. For 10 points, William S. Burroughs lived for four years in what Moroccan city?", "answer": "Tangiers [or Tanjah; prompt on Interzone by asking \u201cwhat real-life city is the basis of Interzone?\u201d] &lt;WA, Literary Legacy&gt;", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": []}